### **Muhammad Abbas**

Karachi, Pakistan | +92-308-5685919 | @mail | @linkedin | @github

# PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Focused **Data Engineer** with a **Bachelor's in Computer Science** from **Habib University**, Distinguished for experience in **Rust** and **Data Science** on top of experience with **Data Engineering tools**, with a track record of collaboratively and independently delivering **convertible PoCs** and then developing **production tools** that saves several runtime hours of cloud machines for fintech industry. Well versed in architectural planning for Big data. Delivering well-documented, tested, and operable code. Efficient in collaborating and communicating new ideas and opinions and evaluating the existing ones

#### TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages: Rust, Python, Scala, C/C++, Golang, SQL (Postgres, MSSQL, MySQL), NoSQL (MongoDB), HTML, CSS, JS (basic)

Data Eng. Tools: Spark, NiFi, Airflow, Databricks, Informatica

Software Frameworks: Axum, Actix, Django, Flutter, RestFramework

Al Frameworks: Tensorflow, PyTorch, JAX, NumPyro

**Cloud, DevOps and API Tools**: AWS, Azure Cloud, GCP, Git, Docker, Kubernetes, Postman, Linux (Longtime Desktop User) **Others**: Polars, Pandas, Design Patterns, Debugging, Root Cause Analysis, Architecture Planning, Working with JSON & Parquet

### **EXPERIENCE**

### **Data Engineer I** | Logiciel Services LLC. — United States

Full-time | May 2024 ——— Present

- Developed Rust pipelines for EOD processing of FIX logs to CAT files, C# pipeline previously running in 500mins, got
  optimized to 50mins with Rust & Nifi, saving around 400 mins daily on AWS machine.
- Orchestrated the data ingestion, transformation and AI pipelines through airflow DAGs, triggering pipelines of Nifi, Spark, Rust and AI (Python) on daily basis.

## **Data Engineer I** | *ImproData* — Victoria, Austrailia

Part-time | Dec 2023 – March 2024

- Worked on Azure Databricks (PySpark) for risk management of cyber-security data, building bronze, silver and gold layers.
- Worked on automated pipeline dev using GCP Cloud Functions to transfer compressed json bulk data from local to GCS & population to BigQuery

### **DevOps Intern** | *Pullflow Inc.* — San Jose, California

Full-time | July 2023 - Aug 2023

- Worked on AWS EKS (Kubernetes) and Docker as I was responsible for designing & implementing the infrastructure that was on AWS to on-premise server.
- Worked on Budibase Dashboarding & hosting it on pullflow subdomain using traefik for loadbalancing.

# **Data Engineering Intern** | *United Bank Limited* — Karachi, Pakistan

Full-time | May 2023 - Jun 2023

- Built a pipeline using Informatica for streaming ingestion of UBL's data from Qatar & Bahrain in Hive Data Lake.
- Participated in architecture analysis of data ingestion to datalake of data from UBL Qatar & Bahrain to ensure that the production AI pipelines running in realtime on UBL Pak's data can be used for data from Qatar & Bahrain.

### **Data Analyst Intern** | *Edlab Pakistan* — Karachi, Pakistan

Part-time | Sep 2021 - Oct 2021

 Worked on Data Collection, Cleaning, Manipulation and Organization using NumPy, Pandas and Excel for Demographic Educational Data

#### **Student Mentor** | *Habib University* — Karachi, Pakistan

Part-time | Aug 2023 - May 2024

- Teaching Assistant for Data Structures & Algorithms: Assisted students during labs and with assignments.
- Git & Github Workshop Instructor: Conducted two workshops on Git and GitHub.
- Teaching Assistant for Data Structures & Algorithms: Assisted students during labs and with assignments DSA.

#### **EDUCATION**

**Habib University** 

**BS in Computer Science** | GPA: 3.31

August 2020 – June 2024

### **PROJECTS**

### **Astroflow** | Django, IBM Cloud, SQLite, Function-as-a-Service, Kubernetes, OpenShift

Nov 2023

- In cursus turpis massa tincidunt dui. Cras pulvinar mattis nunc sed blandit libero volutpat sed. Suspendisse potenti nullam ac tortor.
- Ut consequat semper viverra nam libero justo laoreet sit amet. Feugiat nisl pretium fusce id velit ut tortor pretium.

# **Lox Interpreter** | *Python, numpy. D3.js*

Spring 2022

- Ut consequat semper viverra nam libero justo laoreet sit amet. Feugiat nisl pretium fusce id velit ut tortor pretium.
- In cursus turpis massa tincidunt dui. Cras pulvinar mattis nunc sed blandit libero volutpat sed. Suspendisse potenti nullam ac tortor.

Rusqlite | ET;X November 2021

- In cursus turpis massa tincidunt dui. Cras pulvinar mattis nunc sed blandit libero volutpat sed. Suspendisse potenti nullam ac tortor.